Well, good morning, everyone.
I hope you all are having a wonderful morning.
Thanks so much for worshiping with us.
If I haven't had the privilege of meeting you yet, my name is Ryan, and I am very grateful
to have the opportunity to be one of the pastors of you wonderful people.
Just overwhelmed by the generosity of our congregation as I look at this table full
of Christmas shoeboxes.
Thank you so much for all of you that have participated and that are participating in
other things.
It's just such an encouragement to me and to, I'm sure, these children.
We had 30 boxes come in this week from two different college groups at Shenandoah University,
which was a really cool blessing for me to see as well.
Yeah.
So that's great.
There's a wonderful painting on the stage.
If you don't know why it's there, then that means you didn't come to our worship night
and you should feel condemnation and no, I am kidding.
I am very much kidding.
But Barrett painted this painting for us from Revelation chapter five and we decided to leave
it up because we're actually going to be getting into Revelation a little bit over the next two
weeks.
And so I was thinking about that as we sang a few songs about who God is, that he is worthy
of our praise.
And when we think about who God is, I just think about this image of this land land, that
he is worthy because he sacrificed his life for us.
So let me recap where we've been.
If you're new here, I want to make sure that you have context for the conversation that we're
going to have this morning.
We've been in a sermon series that's been going over frequently asked questions from people
in our congregation.
We got over 20 questions.
We can't answer all of them, but we got some great questions and we've been covering them
week by week.
We're going to wrap up the series next week.
We talked about how to approach the Bible as a unified story.
How do we, if we're going to answer questions from the Bible, how do we even read the Bible
well?
We talked about that.
We talked about politics in the kingdom.
That was fun.
The gospel.
What is the gospel?
How does it work?
How do I know if I'm saved?
We talked about communion and last week we talked about the Holy Spirit.
And as we wrap up the series for the next two weeks, what we're going to do is we're just
going to address a genre of questions that I got.
I would say like 20% of the questions that I got.
So what's 20% of 20?
Somebody do the math quickly.
Four, five.
I graduated from college.
This is great.
Actually, probably more.
I got five or six questions about the book of Revelation, about the end times, about
heaven.
And I was kind of trying to figure out which ones to answer, how to answer them.
And I was dragging my feet and we're getting to the end of the series.
And so I decided I'm just going to try and do my best to broadly answer all of the questions
over the next two weeks.
And because I drug my feet and we got to where we are, honestly, I could not have planned it
this well.
If I tried, I'm not that smart.
But I think it's really a fantastic time, a week after an election, to talk about the
book of Revelation, to talk about the end times, to talk about heaven.
Because over the next two weeks, one of the main things that we are going to address is
if, for those of us that consider ourselves Christians, first and foremost, we are citizens
of heaven.
We are ruled by King Jesus.
And that should impact the way that we live our lives every day.
And so in light of an election, I know that we have a diverse congregation.
And I don't know how you came in feeling this morning, but I know that if you consider yourself
a Christian, that your primary citizenship is in heaven.
And so what better two weeks to look at what the Bible says about heaven and what the Bible
says about Jesus' reign on heaven and earth than these next two weeks.
So let's lean in and let's think about the ways in which the way God rules heaven impacts
the way that we live our daily lives today.
See, as American Christians, I think, at least this is the way that I grew up, I don't know
about you, I tend to think about heaven as a distant place with mostly future implications
for my life.
But when we look at the Scriptures and when we really investigate what the Scriptures say
about heaven, we find out that heaven is actually a place that's much closer than we
realize, and I think it has massive implications for our everyday life.
See, Christians tend to think about, I don't know, again, maybe I'm just bringing my baggage
to you all.
We tend to think about heaven as a place we go when we die.
But when the Bible talks about heaven, heaven is the place where God dwells.
And so in theory, by connection, right?
To be absent with the bodies, to be present with the Lord.
So heaven is where we go when we die.
But it's not, that's not the primary focus of heaven in the Bible.
The primary focus of heaven in the Bible is the one who dwells there eternally, God.
So that's what heaven is all about.
And that's my message.
So let's go home.
No, kidding.
So let's pray, and then we'll kind of do a lot of things, probably too many things for
35 minutes.
So wish me luck.
Thank you.
Father in heaven, Father, Abba, in heaven, the place where you dwell eternally, the God
who was and is and is to come.
We humble ourselves before you today.
We come into your presence expectant.
We want to hear from you.
We want to know how you reign over all of creation, both now and in the future.
And we want that to change the way we live our lives today.
We want that to change the way we interact with our neighbors, our coworkers, our friends
and our enemies so that we can see more visibly your kingdom on earth as it is in heaven, the
place where you dwell.
God, teach us more and more about what heaven is like today.
About how you rule and reign and how we can participate in your kingdom on earth as it is in heaven.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
So I went to Bible college.
Thank you.
And Bible college was interesting, but I remember one class most in particular that was very interesting.
It was my English literature class my freshman year.
And we had a professor by the name of Mr. France.
And Mr. France was a grad student.
And so he was like, he was working on probably a PhD or something.
And he was still, he was teaching classes probably to get free schooling, which is great.
He was kind of a nerd, like the type of nerd that translates Egyptian hieroglyphics in his free time.
And so, but he was young and smart and a student.
But because of all of those things, he wasn't the best professor in the world.
Like I remember one class in particular, we, all of us were there on time.
The class started at 10.
And at about 10.10, Mr. France skateboarded into the classroom with his tie like disheveled and two buttons on his shirt undone.
He was putting his contacts in at the front of the class 10 minutes late.
And you could tell that he had not prepared for the class at all.
And so he decided to put, this was his lesson plan for the day.
He played us a nine inch nails song while he was putting his contacts in.
And when he finished his contacts in his tie, he was like, all right, let's do some literary analysis about what this song means.
What is the symbolism in this song?
And I'll never forget this because I learned a couple valuable lessons that day, believe it or not, from the professor that showed up 10 minutes late on a skateboard, which was fun.
I understood, I learned two valuable lessons that day.
And the first valuable lesson is that literary analysis is difficult, especially when there's poetic imagery and artistic symbolism.
Like it's hard to really grasp what it is that the author is trying to communicate when there's symbols and artistic expressions in them.
So that's the first thing I learned is that it's difficult.
And the second thing that I learned is that I'm not very good at it.
So, the reason I bring that up is because when we come to the book of Revelation, and this is, we're going to spend some time in Revelation today because it's probably the most condensed exploration of heaven and the end times in all of the Bible.
And I think the problem is that we often misunderstand the book of Revelation because, has anybody read it recently?
Pretty confusing, difficult, maybe hard to understand.
And some of you are like, no, no, no, it's not hard to understand at all.
It's really easy to understand.
Send me an email, let's have a meeting, okay?
So, there's a problem in the American church.
One is we either ignore it because it's confusing and difficult and challenging and we just get too scared and overwhelmed and so we don't read it.
Or some of us, we become obsessed with it.
It becomes the primary thing that we read and consume.
And because of some of the material that is out there on the book of Revelation right now in our modern cultural moment,
a lot of us end up being obsessed with it but misunderstanding what it actually is all about.
And so, I think many Christians in the American church, we either totally ignore it or we misunderstand it.
And my goal for today is twofold, and this is why I said it was ambitious.
I want to give us some big picture principles for how we can better understand the book of Revelation as a whole.
And then I want to hop into two specific chapters and kind of take those principles and show you how it works from two chapters specifically.
Does that sound like an okay plan?
Okay.
We did something new today on the back of your bulletins.
There's fill-in-the-blank notes.
So, for all my type A people, there you go.
I can't promise this will happen every week.
We make our bulletins on Thursday morning, and that would mean that I would have to finish my sermon by Thursday morning every week.
It's an ambitious task.
I will attempt it.
But for now, you have one bulletin with notes on it.
We're going to look first at a couple principles of how to better understand the book of Revelation because it's filled with symbolism.
It's from a totally different culture and a genre of literature that we're not familiar with.
And so, we need some guiding principles when we come to the book of Revelation, and then we'll unpack a couple chapters once we get there.
First, in your notes, if you've taken them, the first principle that I would give you as you interact with the book of Revelation.
Also, I forgot to say, after that, at the very bottom, there's some resources.
So, if this piques your interest at all, and you're like, I want to study this book that I've been afraid to study for a long time,
there's a couple of resources there.
Feel free to pick.
I would pick one.
Don't get like, don't go to the Amazon cart and put all four of them in there today because then you'll just be overwhelmed and you won't start it.
But, okay.
Number one, first principle for the book of Revelation.
You and I are not the main characters of the book of Revelation, and the 21st century is not the primary setting.
Does that upset anyone?
Don't tell me out loud.
We'll talk about it later.
See, the book of Revelation was written for us, but it was written for us, but it was not written to us.
We have to understand when we get to books of the Bible, we talked about this in the first message, we have to understand it in light of the original audience.
What was the original author intending to communicate to the original recipient?
That should drive our understanding of the book of Revelation, and this might seem obvious, but the American church, we struggle to do this, I think, with the book of Revelation more than any other book in the Bible.
We struggle with it with lots of books of the Bible because my friend, she's not my friend, she's famous, but I like to call famous people that I listen to on podcasts my friends.
Anybody else do that?
Okay.
Because my friend Jen Wilkin likes to say that we have main character energy, the American church, right?
We have main character energy.
We love to put ourselves at the center of every story.
It is just by the nature of who we are as Americans.
We love to be at the center of the story, and we love to put ourselves at the center of the book of Revelation.
I think there's a lot of reasons for this.
A couple of reasons.
Our imaginations have been captured and influenced by a popular fiction story that was a New York Times bestseller called Left Behind.
Anybody read those?
Yeah, right?
Okay.
So that book is a, look it up, science fiction book.
This book, not a science fiction book.
Okay.
All right.
Just, so we're all in the same.
And if you like, if you like the Left Behind series, that's great.
It's fine.
It is, it is imaginative and cool and there's symbols, but, but we should not use the Left Behind series to help us interpret the book of Revelation because it is a science fiction novel.
I actually read on Amazon today, the New York Times, this is what they said about the Left Behind series.
It combines Tom Clancy-like suspense with touches of romance, high-tech flash, and biblical references.
That's the description of the book.
And some of you did not grow up in the church and you're like, what is this guy talking about?
Okay.
Don't worry about it.
You don't, you don't have the baggage that we have and that is okay.
But anyway, we make ourselves the main character.
Number one, when we're reading Revelation, you and I are not the main characters of the story.
The 21st century is not the primary setting.
Also, I see a lot of modern-day prophets online that are doing their best to interpret the book of Revelation in light of our current cultural moment.
Again, that is making us the primary characters in the primary setting of the book.
And the thing, here's the thing about numbers.
Any of you that work with numbers, any of you that read statistics or studies online, have you ever read a right-leaning study?
And then went and looked for a left-leaning study about the same thing.
And they have the exact same numbers, but they use those numbers to communicate something totally different.
You can, you can, somebody that's smart and cunning can come to the book of Revelation and there's plenty of numbers and plenty of symbols and they can make it say whatever they want to make it say.
Be careful with these types of people.
If we want to understand the book of Revelation properly, we have to do a better job of acknowledging our biases and our culture and allow the Scripture to speak to us in its original context.
Does that sound good?
Principle one.
All right, principle two.
I got to go through these fast.
The numbers and symbols that are confusing to us were clear to them.
This is massive.
This is important.
John was not trying to write some cryptic message that was difficult for everyone to understand.
He was using a popular genre of literature.
Apocalyptic literature was popular in the first century.
These first century people knew what apocalyptic literature was.
They knew how to interact with it.
It was not unfamiliar to them.
Think about the first time Americans, those of us that we grew up on Dr. Seuss poetry, right?
Brilliant.
Masterpiece.
Dr. Seuss is the best.
Now, think about you grew up with Dr. Seuss and then the first time that you ever heard a haiku poem, you were like, this is not a poem.
This stinks.
This is not good literature, right?
But then you learn about it, you understand the mechanics of a haiku poem, and the more you spend time in it, the more you're like, oh, okay, you can see the creativity and the beauty in the masterpiece, right?
Okay, so we don't have a whole lot of apocalyptic literature, especially in that first century apocalyptic literature that we spend time with.
So it's important.
It was not a cryptic message.
It was a message that was a popular genre that included rich symbolism from the Old Testament in the first century, and they would have understood these symbols and these numbers.
And so for us to understand what they mean, we have to work hard to put ourselves in the first century culture, which is why I'm not ready to do a full sermon series in the book of Revelation yet.
Because that means that in order for me to teach it to you well, I will have to immerse myself in the first century Roman culture.
I don't know about you, but I have a toddler, so we're going to do broad brushstrokes for now.
And eventually, I really would like to dive into this because I think it's important.
But one example of symbols in culture.
Okay, I didn't put it up on the slide, but if I were to put up on the slide a red elephant, what would that represent to you?
All right, and then if I put a blue donkey, what would that represent to you?
Cultural symbolism.
You guys know it immediately, right?
It's just in, it is in the fabric of our culture.
And there are symbols throughout the book of Revelation that look confusing to us, but they would have got it immediately.
They wouldn't have had to even think about it or digest it.
Another thing that's important to think about, the book of Revelation was intended to be heard out loud.
And so as the book was being read out loud, these people had much better imaginations than us because they had much better attention span than us.
Because they didn't have the world in the palm of their hands to distract them, right?
These symbols, these numbers, they made sense to the original readers.
Numbers in Hebrew culture in the Old Testament have clear, repeated, and symbolic meanings.
They just, they do, they understand these things.
So because we tend to think we're the main characters and our culture is the primary setting, what we often do is we look at the book of Revelation in one hand, and then in the other hand, we have like the newspaper.
And we're like, what's happening today?
Which sign and symbol can I find from the newspaper today in the book of Revelation?
We often read the book of Revelation with our newspaper in one hand and the book in the other.
And again, we can make our numbers fit with any agenda, but if we want to understand the book of Revelation, the better way to understand the book of Revelation would be to have the book of Revelation in one hand and the Old Testament in the other.
The symbols, the numbers, it is, it is filled with Old Testament references.
There's over 500 Old Testament references in the book of Revelation that has less than 500 verses.
So there's more than one Old Testament reference per verse in the book of Revelation.
That's insane.
And we, as American Christians, again, I'm not picking on you because I'm the same way.
We don't have a robust understanding of the Old Testament.
And so then we come to the book of Revelation and we expect to be able to understand it.
But if we don't understand our Old Testament, we'll struggle.
Okay?
And if you want a newspaper in your hand, last thing, if you want a newspaper in your hand when you read the book of Revelation, get a first century Roman newspaper.
Because the current events that were happening in first century Rome are going to be more easily found in here than what are in our newspapers.
Got it?
Helpful.
Okay.
Third, Revelation was not primarily, this is fun.
Revelation was not primarily written to predict the future, but to encourage the faint.
This book is written by a pastor to churches that he loves.
And these churches are being persecuted mercilessly by the Roman government.
And Jesus gave this vision to this pastor so that he could encourage people that were struggling under Roman oppression, under governmental oppression.
And so I think we kind of missed the main overarching point when we look here and we say, when are all of these things going to happen?
Tell me the future.
And I get it, we all want to know what's going to happen, right?
But at the end of the day, the point of this book, the overarching point, is to encourage believers who are struggling in their relationship with the government.
Which again, is why today is a great day to interact with this book, because some of you are really struggling with how to interact with the government.
And the book of Revelation is meant to encourage believers that are tired, that are exhausted, that don't know what to do.
I just want to prove this to you a little bit, because I know that some of us, we have these ideas in our mind.
And we're like, okay, Ryan, you can say whatever you want, but like prove it from the text.
So, first, the word Revelation.
Revelation chapter 1, verse 1, it says,
The revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave him to show his servants the things that must soon take place.
He made it known by sending his angel to the servant John, who bore witness to the word of God and to the testimony of Jesus Christ.
Even to all that he saw, blessed is the one who reads all these words of the prophecy, and blessed are those who hear and who keep what is written.
First, the word Revelation.
Talked about this at worship night, so if you're here, you already know some Greek, right?
Who was here?
Who remembers Greek?
There were more hands that were here than remember the Greek, but that's okay.
The word for Revelation, it literally is apocalypsis, somewhere in that genre.
We were close.
I went to Bible college.
I didn't go to seminary, so sorry.
You guys got the budget deal on the pastor.
The word literally just means to unveil, to reveal what is previously hidden, but what it has come to us to mean, right?
When we hear that Greek word, we probably think the word apocalypse, and when we think apocalypse, we think end times, disaster.
When the first century readers would hear the apocalypse, they would not be thinking end times, disaster.
They'd be thinking, oh, John is going to reveal to us spiritual truths behind earthly truths.
It's just a word that means to unveil.
It's like unwrapping your Christmas presents.
Anybody like to shake the boxes?
Right?
You shake the boxes.
You know what you asked for.
You're like, I think this might be.
And so you shake, and you think, and you shake, and you think, but there's something joyous about that moment when you get to unwrap it and see it.
That's what John is doing for these first century believers.
He's unwrapping the box.
He's showing these believers what is true in the heavenly realities and how the heavenly realities should impact earthly realities.
He's revealing to us something previously hidden.
The other thing that we struggle with in our culture is the word prophecy to us means only like predicting the future with 100% accuracy in literal things.
That's what we tend to think about when we think about prophecy.
The word prophecy in the Scriptures had multiple meanings.
One was foretelling.
There was some foretelling where prophets would predict things about Jesus.
We all read the, many of us have read like over 400 prophecies about Jesus that were fulfilled literally in his lifetime.
So that did happen, but oftentimes prophecy was foretelling.
It was just proclaiming truth about God.
And so when we think that this book is only telling the future, we're missing some of the nuance of the text.
The other thing too is if we're really concerned about predicting exactly what's going to happen in the future, when you look at, when you look at Scripture as a whole, almost always prophecy is clear in hindsight.
Right?
Prophecy is clear after it happens.
So if your primary goal with the book of Revelation is to figure out what's going to happen before it happens, you're probably not going to get it right.
I think about the story of the road to Emmaus, right?
I just said there were over 400 prophecies about Jesus that he all, that he clearly lived out perfectly.
And after his resurrection, he's walking with some disciples on the road to Emmaus, and they're so discouraged because they thought he was the Messiah, but he died so he can't be the Messiah.
And it says that he told them, he walked them through the entire Old Testament, explaining to them how it was about himself.
And then light bulb flips on.
Oh yeah, 400 prophecies about you are all true, but we miss it until after the point.
And so my whole point here is, when we approach the book of Revelation, don't primarily try and discern exactly what's going to happen, when it's going to happen.
Allow the realities of heaven to encourage you in your everyday life.
Your primary relationship with Revelation should be less about when and how this will all take place, and more about what was, is, and always will take place, and how you're invited to live into that story.
I love the words of Jesus right before he ascends into heaven in Acts chapter 1, verses 6 and 7.
And I'm hammering this a lot because I know the temptation.
As a pastor, I get more questions about the book of Revelation than any other book in the Bible, because we want to know what's going to happen, whether we're scared, or whether we're anxious, or whether we're excited, or whatever it might be.
We want to know, we want to try and predict, we want to figure out where we're at.
And this is one of the last things that Jesus says to his disciples before he heads to heaven.
His disciples say, Lord, will you at this time restore the kingdom of Israel?
That question essentially is, are we in the end times?
Is this the time for the kingdom?
Are you about to do the thing that we thought you were going to do?
And Jesus said to them, it is not for you to know the times or the seasons that the Father has fixed by his own authority.
John, in this conversation, the book, the author of the book of Revelation, Jesus says, it's not for you to know the time.
So then why would Jesus give John a vision, telling him exactly how to predict the time, okay?
It's about encouraging the faint.
I love this quote from Pastor Robbie Gallaty.
I am way behind.
Holy cow.
Okay.
Sorry.
Robbie Gallaty says this, John's goal was not to give a sequential roadmap to predict the return of Christ during the end days.
His goal was to provide a shot of encouragement in the arms of Christians who were being mercilessly persecuted by the Roman government,
and who were thinking to themselves, why are things so bad for the people of God?
This is the original audience.
And what Jesus gives to John is a vision and unveiling of what is truly happening in heaven.
He's telling these believers who are being mercilessly, I got to get better at saying that word,
mercilessly persecuted.
He's telling them there is a truer reality in heaven that you cannot see, but one day you will experience.
And that reality is that Jesus Christ is ruling and reigning in heaven, and he sees your suffering and your persecution,
and he will bring about justice and redemption and victory and reconciliation for the whole world.
That's what the book of Revelation is all about.
It's about encouraging the faint.
And I don't know about you, but I need some encouragement this morning.
Anybody else?
All right.
So let's do that.
Let's encourage each other this morning from Revelation chapter 4 and 5, starting with verse 1 of chapter 4.
So he gives us an intro about what the book's all about.
He writes seven specific letters to the seven churches.
That'll be a fun study one day.
And then the second scene starts, and we get an unveiling of heaven as it is today.
The realities of heaven, an unveiling of what heaven is like, the place where God dwells.
This is how God is ruling and reigning as we speak.
As we enter into worship this morning, we are entering into the heavenly throne room that was, is, and always will be.
After this, John, I looked, and behold, a door standing open in heaven.
And the first voice which I had heard speaking to me like a trumpet said, come up here, and I will show you what must take place after this.
At once I was in the spirit, and behold, a throne stood in heaven with one seated on the throne.
So, if you're in here and you consider yourself a citizen of heaven, this should encourage you.
God is in heaven, and he is seated on his throne.
We need not be afraid.
Everything is under control.
And I don't know which news station you like to listen to, but some of the news stations that you might listen to might be telling you that everything is not under control.
Don't be afraid.
God is seated on his throne.
The door of heaven is open for those of us who have faith to see it.
We are invited.
Christians are invited to live by faith and not by sight.
So, when we get images of the heavenly realms, we're invited to live in light of those realities now, as if they were true and visible, even though we can't see them, we can see them by faith.
And what we can see by faith is that God is seated on his throne.
That heaven is not a distant place with future implications, but a close place with present implications.
John is telling a group of people who are being, here we go again, ready?
Mercilessly persecuted by the Roman government that God is still on the throne.
No matter how bleak things might seem on earth, there is a truer reality being revealed to us in heaven.
If you're taking notes, the God who was, is, and always will be, is seated on his throne.
I love what N.T. Wright says.
It says this, that the powers of the world are simply parodies, cheap imitation copies of the one power who really and truly rules in heaven and on earth.
This is the truer reality that is invisible to us, but visible in heaven.
And if we have eyes to see it, faith to see it, no matter who wins any election for the rest of our lives, Jesus is seated on his throne.
All right, I don't have time to read verses 3 through 7, but I'll summarize it for you, and you can go back and read it later.
We get a description in verses 3 through 7 of what God's throne looks like.
And I wanted to give you an example of how we can kind of unpack some of the imagery of John with some context.
So think Old Testament, those of you that grew up in Sunday school, around God's throne is a rainbow.
What should that bring to mind as we're reading the book of Revelation?
God's promise, Noah, right?
Like, this is what they would have thought as he's reading, and they see a rainbow around the throne of God.
And I think what this rainbow is intended to remind us of is that God was, is, and will deal with sin with both justice and mercy.
That this is how God has always operated, that he has always dealt with sin with both justice and mercy.
That he extends grace and forgiveness to those who would have eyes to see, who would receive it as a free gift.
The God who was and is to come is dealing with sin, both with justice and mercy.
Around the throne are 24 thrones.
Again, numbers, images, they would have understood it.
24 divided by 2 is 12.
We have the 12 tribes of Israel and the 12 apostles of the church.
This is meant to remind us that God, as he's dealing with sin, he is always in partnership with human beings to bring about his mercy to the world.
He partnered with Israel in the Old Testament.
He's partnering with the church in the New Testament.
God is, was, and always will work through human partnerships to bring about his mercy and his justice.
Then we see four living creatures, which have eyes all over.
That's a fun one.
If you ever see somebody try and draw that, really fun.
Four is a number of wholeness in the Bible.
And the, the, the beasts have certain faces.
And essentially the, the symbolism there is to, to symbolize, that's the word I was looking for, the totality of creation.
All of creation.
So here's the main point of chapter, of verses three through seven.
In my opinion, again, I'm not an expert.
Please test this with your own theories.
But I would say this on your bulletin.
God was, is, and will redeem humanity to himself and restore creation to its intended design.
Verses three through seven show us around the throne of God that God is working with humanity to bring about redemption for humans and restoration of all creation.
These are images that on the surface look a little bit scary and confusing to us, but they're actually intended us, intended to remind us of God's eternal character.
That he has a plan to redeem and to restore the brokenness of this world that he is seated on his throne and we can trust him.
All right.
Moving on.
I really have to move fast.
I promise I will.
All right.
Verse eight.
After we see this plan that God is working with human beings to redeem human beings and to restore all of creation.
It says that the, the, the symbols that represent all of creation, they fall down on their faces and day and night they worship God.
Holy, holy, holy, holy, holy is the Lord God almighty who was and who is and who is to come.
They go on worthy.
Are you our Lord and God to receive glory and honor and power for you created all things and by your will, they existed and were created.
Again, hopefully, I hope that we can see how this unveiling of the present reality of heaven might encourage the faint.
Who are being persecuted, who are being marginalized.
John's saying no matter what persecution or suffering or anxiety or fear we might experience on earth, heaven is a real place.
And God is seated on his throne.
Don't be afraid.
Okay.
We go on to verse five.
This is all good news, right?
Lots of good news happening.
God is, is, was, and always will be redeeming humanity, restoring all of creation.
We can trust him even when we can't see it.
All good news.
We get a little bit of bad news in chapter five.
John then sees in the right hand of God seated on the throne, a scroll written on it, both in the back and sealed with seven seals.
And I saw a mighty angel proclaiming with a loud voice, who is worthy to open the scroll and break its seals?
And no one in heaven or on earth or under the scroll or to look into it.
And so I began to open the scroll or to look into it.
John's vision continues.
And this scroll represents God's redemption plan for all of creation.
From beginning to end, God has an eternal plan for how he is going to redeem humanity and restore all of creation.
It's all written down and it's sealed and someone has to open it.
And the question becomes who?
Who can open it?
Who can bring about the reconciliation of all human beings?
Who is powerful enough?
Who is wise enough?
Who is humble enough in all of creation?
And John weeps because he knows from his experience and from his study of history that no one in all of creation is worthy to do that job.
And I think you and I intuitively know the same thing from our personal experience and from our study of history.
Think about the best leaders that you have ever been around.
Think about the best leaders in human history that you have read about.
All of them.
Our best and our brightest are flawed and selfish at the core.
Even if you are extremely optimistic about your presidential candidate, you know that they are not worthy for a job like this.
So we weep.
Until we get to verse 5.
And one of the elders said to me,
Weep no more.
Look or behold, the lion of the tribe of Judah, the root of David, has conquered so that he can open the scroll and its seven seals.
And between the throne, the four living creatures, and among the elders, I saw a lamb.
Symbolism that we even as New Testament Christians get.
I saw a lamb standing as though it had been slain with seven horns and with seven eyes, which are the seven spirits of God, sent out into all the earth.
And he went and he took the scroll from the right hand of him who was seated on the throne.
And when he had taken the scroll, the four living creatures and the 24 elders fell down before the lamb.
This is where it starts to get really, really good.
And I didn't leave myself enough time to preach.
So, sorry.
Jesus, being both fully God and fully man, is the only one worthy to bring about God's plan of redemption.
To redeem humanity and to restore creation.
He is the only one that is worthy of us to put our trust in.
And so if you're in here and you're putting your trust in any other person, in any other leader, in any other political party,
whatever it might be, John is pulling back the curtains of heaven and saying,
do not trust anyone other than the lamb who's been slain, for he is worthy.
But the amazing, wonderful thing is that Jesus' victory does not come the way that we think it's supposed to come.
John hears about the lion of Judah, the root of David, strength, power.
That makes sense.
But when he looks to see this lion, instead he sees a lamb that was slain.
With seven horns and seven eyes.
Again, fun symbolism, right?
We all know what that means.
Seven is the number of completion in Hebrew.
And the horns are representing strength and the eyes are representing wisdom.
What John is saying is that Jesus laying down his life in sacrificial love is the strength and wisdom of heaven.
If you're following along in your notes, there you go.
Sacrificial love is the strength and wisdom of God.
The victory that Jesus has on the cross is not like the victory of this world.
It doesn't make sense.
To the wisdom of this world, our political parties lead with strength and power.
And Jesus leads with sacrificial love.
Again, we could see how this would be an encouragement to a persecuted group with no power or influence to speak of.
John is telling the churches that he pastors through this vision, you will overcome.
You will have victory.
You need only to follow the way of the lamb.
What a timely message for us.
In a time of confusion and discouragement,
God is on the throne.
The lamb who was slain is worthy to bring about God's plan of redemption.
We don't need to be afraid.
We don't need to lash out or fight back.
We only need to follow the example of the lamb.
Loving our enemies and praying for those who persecute us.
This is the wisdom and strength of heaven and we will overcome.
Revelation 5, verses 9 and 10.
After the lamb who was slain takes the scroll and begins the plan of redemption for all creation,
they sing a new song.
Worthy are you to take the scroll to open its seals for you were slain and by your blood you ransomed people for God from every tribe and language and people and nation.
And you have made them a kingdom of priests to our God and they shall reign on the earth.
Taking notes, our response to all of this, to the realities of heaven, our response should be worship and participation.
They fall down and they say, worthy are you.
We should fall down and say, worthy are you.
But look what it says.
It says, you ransomed a people of God from every tribe, language, people, and nation and you made them a priest.
Who is that talking about?
The church.
That's us.
Jesus did this.
He took the scroll.
He opened the seals.
He established a people of God from every language, tribe, nation, and tongue so that we can go about proclaiming his kingdom on earth as it is in heaven.
And in order for us to do this, we've got to get heaven into our bones now.
We've got to remember that Jesus is seated on his throne, that he is worthy, and that the principles of his kingdom are sacrificial love.
This is how we go about being priests.
This is how we go about overcoming.
This is how we go about having peace in the midst of difficult circumstances.
This is how we encourage the faint.
Jesus, who was slain, is seated on the throne.
Let's summarize both of these chapters this way.
Look, the almighty God is seated on his throne.
Don't be afraid.
The slain lamb is worthy to bring about God's eternal plan of redemption and restoration.
Citizens of heaven, take heart.
Be encouraged.
The lamb is overcome.
We've had victory as one.
It is secured.
We might not see it.
We might not experience it fully here on earth, but it is true.
It is a truer reality than what we see with our eyes.
If we would have faith, if we would walk by faith and not by sight, if we would get this reality into our bones.
Imagine what God would do with a kingdom of priests who lived as if heaven's realities were true on earth.
And if you're here and you don't know Jesus, you're not really sure where you're at with this whole thing.
I was just having a conversation with somebody this morning who had a heck of a week.
And she said to me what I've said to many others, and that is, I don't know how people who don't have Jesus do it.
And so if you're in here and you don't know Jesus and you're discouraged and you're confused and you're angry and you're sad and you're whatever mix of emotions you're feeling right now.
I believe that what John wrote down in the book of Revelation is a unveiling of what is true eternally in heaven.
Jesus is on the throne.
There's peace in the midst of your anxiety.
There's victory in the midst of your defeat.
There's salvation from the brokenness of this world.
All you need to do is bow down at the feet of the Lamb and say, worthy are you to receive honor and glory and power and wisdom.
If that's something that you want to do, I'd love to have a conversation with you about that.
Everyone else, you are a kingdom of priests bought with the precious blood of Jesus.
May you go out this week living on mission for the kingdom of God.
Seeing the kingdom of God more visibly on earth as it is in heaven.
Do it with sacrificial love and wisdom.
Let's pray.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for Jesus.
We thank you for this vision, this heavenly unveiling.
God, we probably won't ever understand it fully or completely, but we get the gist.
You're seated on your throne.
You're bringing about the redemption of humanity and the restoration of all creation.
And even though we can't see it, you are the God who was and is and is to come.
And so because we've seen you do it in the past and you've promised to do it in the future,
God, we are going to remain faithful and we are going to persevere because we trust that you are who you say you are.
You'll do what you say you're going to do.
Pray all of this in Jesus' name.
Amen.
Thank you, church.
Spend time with one another.
Greet one another with holy handshakes and hugs.
Go in peace.